<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The king of Denmarkes vvelcome Containing his ariuall, abode, and entertainement, both in the citie and other places.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18684</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852531</idno>
  <idno type="VID">17856</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240894594</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 5194</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117316</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852531e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1132:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The king of Denmarkes vvelcome Containing his ariuall, abode, and entertainement, both in the citie and other places.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Christian --  IV, --  King of Denmark and Norway, 1577-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17856:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17856:1"/>
            <p>THE KING OF Denmarkes vvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: <hi>Containing his ariuall, abode, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement,</hi> both in the Citie and other places.</p>
            <q>Discite Io pean, Io bis discite pean.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Edward Allde</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON Printed by</hi> Edward Allde. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17856:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17856:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The most Joyfull, royall and magnificent</hi> meeting, between our most dreade Soueraigne <hi>Iames</hi> by the grace of God, King of greate <hi>Brittaine, France</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> defendor of the Faith, &amp;c. And <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the 4. King of <hi>Denmarke, Norway, Gothland</hi> &amp; <hi>Vandalls,</hi> Duke of <hi>Sleswicke, Holst, Stormarch, Wagria</hi> and <hi>Ditchmarke,</hi> Count of <hi>Osdenburge</hi> and <hi>Delmenhurst,</hi> &amp;c And Brother to our moste Gracious Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> vppon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Thames,</hi> neere vnto <hi>Grauesena,</hi> On Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 18. of Iuly, Anno. 1606.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Written in a discourse from a Gentleman to a friend of his</hi> in the northerne parts: together with the manner of the two kinges cōming to <hi>Greenewich,</hi> the entertainment there and in other places, &amp; their moste pompous passage through the Citie of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, albeit out of mine owne disposition as wel as out of the difficultye of these times (which from a late customarie title, haue takē vnto themselues a more large Pattent of misconstruing mens wordes, or misaplying their meaninges (how euer it sauour of a vertuous Innocency) then hath been exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised in the daies of our fore-fathers) I haue beene euer a moste vnwilling Newes-sender: yet considering the threefold blessinges which like a Diuine imbroderye
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17856:3"/> makes our Nation most admirable, both in the eyes &amp; eares of al domestique &amp; forraine people: to wit a King holy &amp; magnanimous. Royal issue &amp; prosperous, &amp; Imperial alliāce, faithful &amp; inuincible, haue at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent so inflamed both my heart and eyes: the latter with admiration, the first with a deepe and waightie consideration: how aboundandantlye wee are to praise the Maiestie of Maiesties, who to the dayes of our peace, hath added th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se ioyfull and not formerlye hearde-of howers of moste vnspeakeable happinesse, wherein we are blest to beholde our nation gouerned by so puissant a King, who with his birth-right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, hath brought vs peace, without limytation, which albeit before we inioyed in our bosomes, yet we wanted in our garments, succ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssion to our state, such as confound all the thoughts of the ambitious, and that affinitie, concord, and allyance, which hath not onelye taken frō enuie her sting, but euen giuen to the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st feare a most valiant and resolued courage: nay more, to behold a stranger king (stranger I meane as to our eies and the distance of Kingdomes how euer the neerest of all great ones in blood and friendship) a King I say blest with all the felicities of power, peace and fertilitie: not to send his loue, but to bring his loue: not to protest by the mouth of others, but to witnesse with his owne words: not to giue vs hope what he will be, but to assure vs in himselfe what hee is: as it is an example exceeding all examples, a blessednesse beyond the compasse of memorie, and an instance (how euer imitable in parte) yet in the whole beyond the records of our longest Chronicles; so let vs all euen sanctifie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17856:3"/> both with heart and voice, the memorie of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all King of <hi>Denmarkes</hi> comming to our kingdome, and euen teach it to our children, from generation to generation, that euen till the last day it may bee kept as fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh in mens mouthes and eares, as at this present: and that succeeding ages who shall but heare the name of our Royall Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> from whose happie coniunction is discended both this felicitie and all others: which our Children and Childrens Children shall hereafter hope for, may with the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t say, <hi>O quam te memorem virgo, O dea certe!</hi> From these considerations accōpained with this so strange though long wisht for, &amp; most happy meeting of our King and his dearest brother, the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> I was stirred vp to write you such particulars as eyther my selfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly noted, or else I receiued from others, which were eye witnesses.</p>
            <p>THe seauenteenth day of Iulye beeing Thursday, the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> with about seauen goodly tal shippes, sayling alongst the coast of England, came towards the euening vp to the Riuer of Thames, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer against <hi>Graues-end,</hi> where hee cast Anchor: and notice beeing giuen to our King, whose Court was then at <hi>Greenewich,</hi> being foure mile from London, his Maiestie sent certaine of principall account downe to <hi>Graues-end</hi> to the King, but night beeing come, and the Watch in orderlie and warl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke sort sette, the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> slept that night aboord his shippe. The next day being the eighteenth of Iuly, &amp; Friday, our King attended by the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> and Duke of <hi>Linox,</hi> the Earle of Nottingham Lord
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17856:4"/> Admirall, the Earle of Suffolke, Lord Chamberlaine and diuers other Earles, Barrons, Knights, Pensioners, and Esquires, to the number of some fiue or sixe and thirtie Bardges, or there abouts, tooke his Maiesties bardge &amp; went downe to Grauesend; where first the noblemen went aboord the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> ship, &amp; were most graciously receiued. after them the Young Prince, whome the King culd &amp; imbraced moste lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly in his armes, expressing a most tender &amp; royall affection: thē came our King himselfe, between whom &amp; the king of <hi>Denmark,</hi> past such imbraces, such words &amp; such royal accōplemēts of most vnuiolable &amp; inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressable affection, that I am neither able to concejue it, nor worthie to deliuer it, such wordes and thoughts being fit for no meaner bosomes.</p>
            <p>The Ship wherein the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> went, was a moste goodly and famous Vessell, and as some Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men reported, about the burthen of ten or twelue hundred tunne, shee boare in her, three tyer of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, all brasse, both great and large: her poope, her forecastle and Beake-head, were all fayre carued and ritchly guilt, so were the port-holes for her peeces, her tops, top-masts &amp; other places: her flagges, Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Pendants were all blewe and white: in her waste and vpper workes stood a Guard of Harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bushes all in blew Doublet, white hattes with blew and white bandes, Cassocks and breeches made neare our English fashion, all of blew cloath, and stript thicke with blew &amp; white silke lace, blew Stockings and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low silke Garters▪ vpon the toppe of the Poope stood about foureteen trūpeters, besides drūmers, al in white
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17856:4"/> Hats, with bandes imbroadered with golde, white sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Doublets, laide with watchet silke and siluer lace: their hose of watchet brancht Veluet, and layd with watchet silke and siluer lace: their Cloakes of blew cloath, garded about with fiue or sixe gardes of watchet Veluet, and laide on with watchet silke and siluer twiste: their Trumpets all siluer and fayre guilt, their Bandroles of watchet silke and siluer, and fayre Banners, containing the Kings armes. Neerer to the Kinges Person, and as it were in nature of our Kings Guard of Gentlemen Pensioners, stood a greate sorte of handsome Gentlemen, with fayre Halberts in their handes, white Hats with golde imbroadered bandes, Casso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks and breeches of watchet Veluet, guarded thicke with a broad lace of watchet silke, siluer, and golde, their Cassocks linde thorowe with changeable Taffata, watchet, and crimson: white Satten Doublets laide with watchet silke and siluer lace, guilt Rapiers &amp; daggers, &amp; in general, euerie mans apparrell made neere to our present english fashion; then were there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure young Youthes, the Kinges Pages in white Hats, with golde imbrodered bands, Doublets &amp; hose of watchet Satten laide with siluer Lace, and Cloakes of watchet cloath, garded with some foure gardes of watchet Veluet, and laid on with watchet silk &amp; siluer twist: Diuers other inferior officers there were in watchet cloath Cloakes garded with watchet Veluet: The next of al to the kings person were about sixe very graue auncient and worthye persons of his Majesties priuie Counsell: next them stood about some twentie or aboue, gallant and braue Gentlemen, some of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17856:5"/> Maiesties Bed-chamber: some appertaining to his highnesse person in other neere offices. In all and of all sortes, that were attendant vpon the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> excepting &amp; omitting Saylors, and such whose offices were onely at Sea: the whole number as it was faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reported, came to three hundred and fourteene, or there abouts. After the Kings had beene priuately to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a good space, and that accompliments and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther entertainments on ship-boorde were ended▪ the two famous Kings came forth together, and our King presented to the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> his owne priuie Bardge, which Bardge was made in fashiō of a Tower, or little Castle, all close with glasse windowes, and casements faire carued, and guilt, and wrought with much▪ Art: the roofe of it was made with battlements, pynacles, pyramides, and fine imagerie: it was towed by an other Bardge, in which was about some thirtie Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es or aboue: into this Bardge went the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> our King, the yong Prince, and some others of the most especiall account, both of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>England:</hi> into other Barges, and other boates appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the purpose, were the rest of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markes</hi> Traine receiued.</p>
            <p>As soone as the two Kings were in the Bardge, not onely that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip wherein the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> himselfe went, but also all the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st let flie all their ordinance in most gallan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sort, euen to the amazement of the ayre, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>light of the beholders.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be noted by the way, that the shippe where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> went, was Castle-like diuided into euery office and place of state, as greate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17856:5"/> Chamber, Presence chāber, Priuie chamber, &amp;c. And those chābers verie richly hung with hangings of state, and ordered according to the dignitie of the places; In maner aforesaide, the two Kinges with both their traynes (which did euen as it were almost couer the Thames) rowed vp to Greenewich, where they lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the Kings stayres, where the water being some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too low, there was a long Table laide from the staiers to the bardge to land vpon, where our King out of his great grace, loue, and royaltie, gaue the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> the first place, and right hand. When they were both landed, our King with most louing and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der imbracements, gaue (as it seemed to vs that were there admirers) a most kinde welcome to his dearest brother, and so as it were arme in arme, the Nobles and Gallants of England, and the like of Denmarke▪ going two and two together before the Kings, they marched from the water stayres, to the great Gate of the Court, and so vp the great Hall and the stayres, into the great Chamber, thence into the presence, and so into the priuie Chamber, from whence it may bee supposed the two Kinges went to the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Chamber (who as then had layne in about some fortnight or more) there being nothing more to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired, either of her Maiestie, or her royall brother, then the sight of each other: How euer it was, what loue, what accompliments, what repetitions of naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections pasted betweene them is not for vulgar minds to imagine, sith none but so great hartes knowe them.</p>
            <p>On Saturday in the morning, being the xix▪ of Iuly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17856:6"/> the two Kings attended with diuerse Noble men and others, ride to <hi>Eltham</hi> Parke hard by Greenewich, where his Maiestie hath a verie faire house, and there they hunted and killed Bucks, and so returned to the Court to Greenwich to dinner, where out King fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> most royally in the log<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings appointed for the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> being the two great Towers and Galleries within the Tilt-yard, which were so well marshalled and contriued, that neither the numbers to be receiued found desease, the attendants trouble, nor the number of vaine gazers (in which our Nation is more rich then any Kingdome) want of their foolish eyes satisfaction, then for the accates and cheare, flesh, fish, foule, beare, ale, and wines of all sortes, it was so royally superabundant, that neyther malice nor detraction could say, but it was most worthily magnificent, and by the way in that so great a feast, where liberalitie with an open hande threwe inticing baites of surfaite abroad, which might euen haue drawne temperance it selfe to haue erred in his owne disposition: I gathered and obserued this note, that how euer the Kingdome of <hi>Denmarke</hi> hath in precedent times, beene either commended or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, for the free-hearted intertainment, or to great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in drinke, yet these (I meane the meaner sort of this royall Kings followers, in whom euer is soonest discerned the most common errour) did showe at this great feast, where they could but wish and haue it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected▪ nay, where many men of many Nations, I knowe, would haue esteemed it more barbarous to haue refused drinke, then disgrace to bee drunke:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17856:6"/> such discreete temperance, refusing with such modest courtesie, and shunning surcharge, with such pleasing affabilitie, that in my conceit they exceeded the seuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Italian: sure I am, for our owne Nation, I haue neither at home, nor abroad seene them more modest, I may wel say no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so respectiue, nay into such a beleefe, and expectation, had former reportes drawne mee, that their first abstinence I imputed to inacquaintance, feare of disgrace, and seueritie of more temperate go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours: but when I sawe all those obstakles recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, and freedome lent euen to the freenesse of their natures, I sawe them continue their good ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and peacefull modestie vnder such a constant rule, that the meanest might some times bee an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to some of ours, that haue or sue for much high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re places.</p>
            <p>After dinner was ended, and sometime spent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Kings in priuate, the King of <hi>Denmake</hi> came downe through the priuie Gardens into the Tennis-Court, where he sate and sawe diuerse sets played at the Tennis, betweene a French Gentleman and one <hi>Webbe</hi> an English Gentleman: and because I had in that Tennis-court, by reason that I stoode a good space opposite against his Maiestie, a perfite and full view of him, I will as neare as I can deliuer you his discription, according to mine owne coniecture.</p>
            <p>First, for his Maiesties stature, it is tall, but not of the tallest sort of men, such as a man shoulde make a question of a taller, but of that mediocritie of tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which is most pleasing in the eye and sense of the best iudgement: his haire is of a whitish
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17856:7"/> browne: his beard somewhat whiter then his head: his cheekes he keepeth smooth without haire: his haire vppon his chinne about three-fingers long, cutte of an euen cutte: in his cheekes hee hath a pure and fresh blood: his countenance cheerefull and amiable: his fore-heade white and hie: his eyes bright and liuely: In all; his face is full, rounde, and enriched with beautie: and to speake without errour, such and so like, that any one that hath beholde her, might chalenge him by the face of the Queenes Maiestie his Sister. Hee is of bodie strongly made, broade, large, and of the best composition, hee appeares bigge vnder his waste, hath an exceeding cleane made legge, and a delicate fine made foote: to conclude, his proportion shewes him to bee a man of greate strength, actiuitie, and indurance, such as are the markes of the best Conquerours. The apparell which that day he wore, was a Doublet &amp; Hose of a kinde of Bryer-ball coloured Satten, plaine, and onely cut with a byas cutte, the fashion, such as is at this day most of request in this Kingdome: hee wore a paire of white Silke Stockings, and a paire of blacke Spanish leather shooes: about his arme he wore a faire Scarfe, and on his heade he had a gray Beuer Hat, with a Hat-band of Pearle, and Diamonds set in Gold-smiths worke, and a Iewell of Diamonds, which held vp the right side brimme of his hat: in my conceyte of price not to bee valued.</p>
            <p>On Sunday being the twentieth day of Iulie, all Courtiers, euen from the best to the meanest, gaue their attendance in their best gallantrie, the Guarde
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17856:7"/> in their rich Coats, all studded ouer with studdes of Golde and Siluer, and faire guilt Halberts in their handes, stoode on each side from the presence Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber doore, to the farther end of the long Gallery next to the Chappell: the Gentle-men Pencioners, some in cloth of Golde, some in cloth of Siluer, Veluet, or Satten layde with Golde or Siluer lace, the meanest all with guilt Pollaxes in their handes, armed with vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, studded with Golde, and tasseld with coloured Silks &amp; Golde or Siluer, stood from the one end of the presence Chamber to the other, euen to the doore of the Lobby which goeth into the priuie Chamber: and when all thinges were in a readinesse, the Nobilitie and Counsaile of England, and the counsaile and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of <hi>Denmarke</hi> going two and two together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the two kinges, verie rich, and in great state fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed through both the former Guards, to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: where after prayers ended, they returned againe into the presence in like statelye fashion, where that day our King feasted the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> in most sumptuous manner, Drummes beating, and Trumpets sounding ouer all the Pallace. Had a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger▪ starued wretch beene but brought thither, to haue behelde the aboundance of meate, without doubt I am perswaded it would haue filled his stomacke: euen plentie breeding a loath, and the open hande of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie stopping the mouth of Desire, insomuch that many refused, what they most craued, because it came so bountifully without asking; and what was most both to be admyred and praysed. Al this infinit worlde of abundance was gouerned by such a discreete and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17856:8"/> euen hand of well experienst iudgement, that there was neither seene lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>shment in the expence, nor dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in the vse, but all thinges discharged bountifully, royally, &amp; without any distast or smallest showe of the least discontentment.</p>
            <p>On Munday the one and twentieth day of Iuly, both the Kinges hunted in <hi>Greenewich</hi> Parke, and dined at the White Tower on the top of the hill, in the Parke, the Earle of Northamton hauing the keeping thereof.</p>
            <p>Tuesday the xxij. of Iuly, and Wednesday the xxiij. were spent in hunting at <hi>Eltham</hi> and in feasting. On Thursday the foure and twentyeth of Iuly, both the Kinges with their traines, which contained great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, roade in progresse to <hi>Theobalds</hi> neare <hi>Waltham,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twelue miles from the Cittie of <hi>London,</hi> and being in the house of the moste Noble and worthie Earle of Salisburie, where vppon the approach of the Kinges Maiesties, there were manie verie learned, delicate, and significant showes and deuises presented vnto them, which I wil omitte amply to discribe, because my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture may erre from the drift of the inuentor, and I hould it a capitall offence by a sleight imagination to misconster a fayre inuention; and there is no doubt but the author thereof who hath his place equall with the best in those Artes, will himselfe at his leasurable howers publish it in the best perfection. Yet to giue you a little taste of what came nearest to my vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there was at the entrance of the Gates, planted a goodly Tree with leaues, and other ornaments resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling a great Oake: the leaues cut all out of greene
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17856:8"/> silke, and ser so artificially, that after certaine speeches deliuered, and Songes of <hi>Welcome</hi> sung, as the Kinges Majesties passed away, euen in a trice, all the leaues showred from the tree, both vppon the heads and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of both the Kinges, and of a great multitude of their followers: vppon euerie leafe beeing written in golde Letters this word (<hi>Welcome</hi>) and vppon some twice (<hi>Welcome</hi>) and the better to put your eares in tune, beeing duld with this my ill pend discourse, I wil set you downe heere the Song of Welcome, which was sung before both the Kings: The Stanzaes by a single voice, the Chorus by a whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort of voices.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17856:9"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="song">
                        <head>The Song at <hi>Theobalds.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>IF euerie Ioy now had a tongue,</l>
                           <l>And all the seuerall thoughts were sung,</l>
                           <l>Vnder this happie roofe,</l>
                           <l>They could make proofe,</l>
                           <l>How much they doe reioyce,</l>
                           <l>In one, the Maisters voice:</l>
                           <l>and that is <hi>welcome</hi> still.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Hayle double flame of Maiesties,</l>
                           <l>Whose luster quicken's: blindes not eyes,</l>
                           <l>Who euer saw such light</l>
                           <l>would wish for night?</l>
                           <l>Stay, stay, we may reioyce,</l>
                           <l>And keepe our constant voice,</l>
                           <l>which is your <hi>welcome</hi> still.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When two Sunnes shine, the ample day</l>
                           <l>Should not so haste it selfe away:</l>
                           <l>A feare to loose destroyes</l>
                           <l>almost our Ioyes,</l>
                           <l>But we must so reioyce,</l>
                           <l>As we make good our voice,</l>
                           <l>of <hi>welcome, welcome</hi> still.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Chorus.</stage>
                        <lg>
                           <l>And would you euer stay,</l>
                           <l>And make it lasting day,</l>
                           <l>Tis <hi>welcome, welcome</hi> still.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17856:9"/>
            <p>After the two kinges with great state and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence were entred the house, it is not to be imagined but beleued, that there wanted no meanes either of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise, pleasure, entertainment, feasting, or what else might glut the heart with contentment, but was there with the most liberall hand, willing heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented spirit powered foorth, no man reprehended for giuing, but many for not taking.</p>
            <p>On friday being the fiue and twentieth day of Iuly, both the Kinges went and hunted the Stagge in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham Forrest, where the heat of the day, the dust from the earth, and the busie flies in the woodes, I thinke took from the Kinges maiestie of <hi>Denmarke</hi> the best part of his delight in the hunting: after they had kilde a brace or two of Staggs, they returned backe to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balds,</hi> where they spent that night: and the next day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Satterday, The six &amp; twentieth day of Iuly, in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate mirth and feasting.</p>
            <p>On Sunday being the seauen and twentieth day of Iuly, as if the noble Earle of <hi>Salisburie</hi> ment to make a distinguishment or difference twixt daies, and to crowne the Saboath with the greatest glorie, the feast, pompe, and bountie, (though the former was almost more then thought could comprehend) seemed euen to double in his encrease of greatnes. Flesh and fish of all sorts fitte for the vse of man, and the most dainty, the most abundant were so mingled and heaped to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, that it was hard to distinguish of which kind there was greatest plentie, each dish that was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp, especially bakd meates and others fitte to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, hade little pendants with the hatchment or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17856:10"/> armes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Denmarke</hi> vpon them, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (in Golden letters) written <hi>Welcome</hi> &amp; <hi>Welcome still.</hi> Many according to the opinion of the eye, which euer is farthest in loue with the last obiect, held this daies feast, the greatest of al other, although the other might well hold a superlatine in any reasonable iudgement: how euer, tis most certaine they were all most royall, &amp; abounded. At the Kings departure the Earle of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie</hi> presented to the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> a fayre Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie Horsse, a faire English Horsse, a goodlye Mare, and two daintie Tracconers for his Maiesties iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saddle, all couered with cloathes of fugard cloath of siluer, richly frindged and adorned.</p>
            <p>On Munday being the eight and twentie day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both the Kinges Majesties after Dinner, departed in great state and gallantrie from <hi>Theobaldes</hi> (where I dare sweare the Noble Earle could haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to haue enioyed them a much longer season) and thence returned backe vnto <hi>Greenewich,</hi> where they spent Tuesday, the nine and twentieth day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Wednesday the thirtieth day of Iuly, in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, feasting, and other priuate delights. On Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesday at night, the Youthes of Paules, commonlye cald the Children of Paules, plaide before the two Kings, a playe called <hi>Abuses:</hi> containing both a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie and a Tragedie, at which the Kinges seemed to take delight and be much pleased.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, beeing the one and thirtieth day of Iuly, after Breakefast was ended, both the Kings with their moste ample Traines, tooke Bardge at Greenewich, and in the moste solemne manner
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17856:10"/> that might bee, came vppe to the Tower at London, landed at the Kinges stayres, tooke viewe of the Wharfe and Ordinance, and also of the Tower, who then was trymde and adorn'd in her best and moste warlike Ornaments: there the Lorde Mayor of the Cittie of London, the two Sheriffes, and almoste a worlde of Earles, Barrons, Knightes and Esquyres, met the two Maiestyes: there the Lorde Mayor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to our King his Sword, and receiued backe from our King his Scepter, which hee boare before the two Majestyes. This doone, the two Kinges mounted vppon two goodlye Horses of like colour, like Plumes all white, and like Barbes or Capary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of inuerted Golde and Siluer. In like manner, all the Nobilitie and Gallantrye both of Court and Cittye were mounted vppon greate Horses, some with plumes of Feathers: some with ritch imbrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Saddles: some with caparisons: some with most costly Foote-cloathes: and other men of other fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being mounted according to the qualitie of their places, were in a moste gallant readinesse to attend the two royall Kinges in their hye pompe, cleane thorough the moste famous Cittie of <hi>London,</hi> which that you may the more truely descerne the greatnesse of the state, I will first deliuer you the manner of their passage.</p>
            <p>First road some xx. &amp; odde of the Knight Marshals men for clearning the way, in white Hats, with greene &amp; white bandes, white Fustian Doublets, and greene Cloath-hose. After them roade all our Kings Trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters sounding their trumpets, behinde whom roadeour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17856:11"/> Sergeant Trumpeter with his Mace: After him rode one of the King of <hi>Denmarkes</hi> Drums, hauing on each side his horse hanging a Kettle Drum, which hee beate with two red sticks, made like two morter pestles, after him roade al the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Trumpeters, soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Trumpets: then roade all our Kinges Groomes and Messengers of the Chamber: after whome followed one of our Purseuants at Armes; then roade mounted on great Horses ritchly furnished and themselues adorned in most costly and rich suites, by two and two, all the Knights and Gentlemen Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, and Knights &amp; Gentlemen, our kings sworne Seruants. After them roade likewise by two and two mounted also vpon great Horses, ritchly trimde and themselues verie rich (after the English fashion) all the king of <hi>Denmarkes</hi> Gallants and ordinatie Seruants: After them roade another Purseuant at Armes: then roade al the Knights and Gentlemen of our kings Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Chamber, Bed-chamber, and places of especiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: then the king of <hi>Denmarks</hi> of like place and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: then a Herrald at armes: after him all our Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and Vicountes: then the Lord Bishops in their Rochets, then the Maisters of Request: then all our Earles, according to their places, not being of the Counsaile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then the Lords of our kinges Priuie-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, and them of the king of <hi>Denmarkes</hi> Counsell: then our Lord Treasurer with his white staffe, &amp; the Lord Chauncelor with the Pursse, and the Lord Mayor of the Cittie: then the Duke of <hi>Lynox</hi> all alone: then the Sergiants at armes with their Maces, then <hi>Garter</hi> king at armes, and all the Gentlemen Vshers: then the Lord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17856:11"/> Admirall, bearing the sworde, and the Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine with his white staffe: after whome roade the yong Prince, mounted vpon a most delicate Courser: after him on the right hand road the king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and on the left hand our King, about whome went all our Kinges footemen, in rich coates of Crimson Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, yellow Satten Doublets, yellow Satten Hose, and yellow Stockings. Close behinde the Kings road the Earle of Worcester, master of the horse: after whom followed almost an hundred or more Gentlemen, the Kings seruants, and on each side went on foote the King of <hi>Denmarkes</hi> Guard of Harquebushes, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hundred or more: In this stately equipage they departed from the Tower-hill, at whose depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were shot from the Tower, and the Wharfe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout some seauen score great shot, being all Cannon, Demy-cannon, Basilisco, and Culuering, besides Chamber peeces a great number, at the entring of Tower streete, sate all the children of Christs Church Hospitall, in their blew coates, together with their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours in their liueryes: from Tower-streete to White-hall being neere two miles in length, all the streets through which their Maiesties did passe, were rayled according to the bignesse of the streete, with railes of framed tymber about twentie foote wide, the one side being but with a single raile, against the which the people and beholders might leane: the other side with a double rayle, some halfe a foote or better from the ground boorded vnderfoote, and seated within, and both the rayles before and behinde, were all coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ground with blewe cloath. Within these
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17856:12"/> double Rayles thus hung, sate the Maisters, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and whole Liuereys of euerie seuerall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie through the Cittie of London, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes extended their length from Tower-streete to Temple Barre, being somewhat more then a Mile: before the Rayles, and before each seuerall Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, stoode the Batchelers of eache seuerall Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, in Satten, Veluet, and other Silke Doublets, and Hose, Golde Chaynes about their neckes, and some Pearle Chaynes, and white Staues in their handes: Alongest the Rayles cleane through out, were fastned all the Banners, Cornets, Flagges, Bandrels, Ensignes, and Pendants, belonging to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie seuerall Companie, contayning within them all the Armes, Deuises, and Honors any way belonging to anie of the same seuerall Companies: all the houses in euerie streete, through which the two Maiesties did passe, had their Penthouses and Walles couered, some with Arrasse, some with Tapistrie, some with Turkie worke, some with other Ornaments, according to the abilitie of the dwellers, to the great delight of all iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall beholders, and to the amazement of such as had not formerly seene the like sights: for the clearing of the middle streete, in which the Kings were to passe, that none but such as were appointed for seruice might abide or pester the same, there were appointed for the Cittie two Prouost Marshals, who mounted on horse-backe in Veluet Coats, red Scarfes, Golde Chaines, and plumes of Feathers road vp and downe, the one attended with eight men in yellowe Fustian Doublets and Hose, white Hattes, redde Feathers,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17856:12"/> and redde Scarffes; the other with as manie in like suits, and white Hattes, white Feathers, and white Scarffes. To second these, were the Constables of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie Warde, with seuerall bandes of Halberders, who kept euery thing in such peaceable order, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was seene rude or vncomely.</p>
            <p>The Kinges Maiesties in manner before prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, passed from Tower-streete downe Marke Lane, thence downe Fanchurch-streete, so vp Gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streete, and then downe Cornehill to the Conduite before the Royall Exchange, which that day ran with Claret-wine: vpon the toppe of the Royall Exchange sate all the Cittie Trumpetters, who during the Kings passage sounded their Trumpets most excellently: then the Kinges passed downe through the Poultrie, till they came to the great long Conduite in the neather ende of Cheapeside: vppon the toppe of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duite, was the modell of a faire Garden, and at one ende an Arbour most delicately made in the figure of a square Canapie, portraiting out in boughes the semblance of Pillars, Pinacles, and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bost worke. This Arbor was all adorned with fruits of all so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes, as Apples, Peares, Plums, Melons, and such like: within the Arbor was a consort of lowde Musique, signifying (as some imagined) the Bower of the nine Muses. This Conduite also that day ranne Claret-wine: from thence the Kings passed vp Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, till they came as hie as the Horse-head Tauerne, from whence there was made a Scaffolde of a prettie height, all lined, hung, and couered ouer heade with blewe cloath: In this Scaffolde sate the Recorder
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17856:13"/> of the Citie, and foure and twentie Aldermen all in their Scarlet Gownes: The Recorder vppon the two Kings approach descended from his seate, and made a most famous and worthie Oration: which ended, hee presented to the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> a most rich present as from the whole body of the Citie: this done, and the Recorder taking again his place, the two Kings ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as hie as the Old-change: from the corner of which street ouerthwart the whole breadth of Cheepside, was built and raised vp a most stately, and well conceyted Pegne, or Pageant, into the depth and secrets whereof I do not intend to wade, because it is expected to bee published presently by the Authour that made it, onely those tastes that mine eie did gather by the view, I will deliuer vnto you: First the middle part betweene the two Arches, for some ten or twelue foote hie from the ground, was represented a Sea, with sundrie Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, Sea nymphs, and others singing within the same, and Musike consorting their voyces: ouer it as it were presenting the Ile of Britaine within the Sea, &amp; round about euen from the ground to the toppe, being as I coniectured aboue fortie foote, were nothing but crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie rocks, adorned with foure most stately Pyramides, which standing on each side the Arches, rise from the ground aboue the toppe of the Arches: Iust ouer the right hand Arch, was <hi>Neptune</hi> all in blew, with his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in his hand, and mounted on a Sea-horse of siluer, sitting as in the Sea: ouer the left hand Arch likewise, in an other Sea-caue, sat <hi>Mulciber</hi> the god of Mettals with all such M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttals as this Ile affoordeth, as Copper, Tinne, Leade, Iron, and such like, mounted vppon a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17856:13"/> Dragon: and vnder each foote a peece of great Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Ouer both these Arches the Rockes rose a great height, and were supported on each side by two great Giants: and on the toppes of those two Rockes stoode the Armes of great <hi>Bryttain</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> ioyned together, the one side supported by one of the Supporters of England, the other by one of the Supporters of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> betweene these Rockes rose a great height higher, like the heade of a fine Turret, with a Pyramides on the toppe of all, vnder which stoode the greate hatchment of greate <hi>Brittain,</hi> and within it sate enthroned (as I conceiued) the genious of Concorde: who vppon the neere approach of the Kings, was by a quaint deuise let downe in her throne, to the lower and middle concaue, where setting open her doores, and deliuering a long speech to the Kings, she discouered to their Maiesties the modell of a faire citie, and much other treasures: there sate the genious of the citie of London, who deliuered to the Kings a long speech in Latin, so did <hi>Neptune</hi> also: the Sea-Nymphs sang in Latin, and the musick was wondrous delightful: the Pageant was wondrously adorned with many guilt columbs, rich banners, &amp; guidons and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie shields, with sundrie learned deuices: after the kings were past through this Pageant, they came into <hi>Paules</hi> churh-yard, where ouer against <hi>Pauls</hi> schoole sat al the petty Canons &amp; singing mē belonging to the great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> amongst whō were mingled a cōsort of cornets, Sagbuts, &amp; other wind instrumēts: at <hi>Pauls</hi> schoole doore was a little scaffold reard &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with cloth of gold, from whence was a most elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17856:14"/> oration made to the two Kings in Latin: from thence both the two Maiesties did depart, and riding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longst <hi>Pauls</hi> churchyard, came to Ludgate: thence they road downe Ludgate-hill, till they came to Fleetstreet Cunduit, from whence as soone as the Kinges appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, was heard a moste excellent consort of stil musick, which inuiting the two Kings to lift vp their eyes, they might beholde a verie fine artificiall sommer bower of greene bowes diuided with curtaines of crimson taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatie, the top of the Arbor made canapie wise and hung round about with this inscription, <hi>Deus nobis haec ocia fecit;</hi> and after, a moste excellent song sung dialogue wise, containing these wordes.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shepheard:</speaker>
               <l>Sweet Ioe vouchsafe once to impart,</l>
               <l>did euer liue so coy a lasse,</l>
               <l>that vnto loue was neuer moued?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shephardesse:</speaker>
               <l>Yes Shephard She that has the hart,</l>
               <l>and is resolud her life to passe:</l>
               <l>neither to loue or be beloued.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He:</speaker>
               <p>She sencelesse liues, without affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>She;</speaker>
               <p>Yet happie liues, without subiection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He;</speaker>
               <l>To be pluckt are Roses blowne,</l>
               <l>To be mowed are meddowes growne:</l>
               <l>Iemmes are made but to be showne,</l>
               <l>And woman's best—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>She:</speaker>
               <p>To holde her owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17856:14"/>
            <p>The Kings might behold within the Arbour, a faire Shepheard courting a coy Shepherdesse, who had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered him that she would loue him, when she could behold two Sunnes at one time of equall brightnesse: when there were two Maiesties of like splendor, or two Kings in one state, with many such like imagined im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilities, which now he shewed her were come to passe, approouing those two kings two glorious Suns, two Maiesties, and what else she had reputed impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible: After these speeches which held a pretty space, the Musicke plaied, and there was another song sung of farewell: at the ende whereof, the Kings Maiesties departed, and so roade along through Fleetstreete to Temple-barre, where the Lord Maior of the Citie taking his humble leaue of the two Kings, and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing many gracious thanks, had the sworde deliuered him backe, and himselfe redeliuered the Scepter, and so withall the rest of his brethren, who mounted vpon their foote-cloathes, richly trapt in goldē trappers came to meete him, they departed into the Citie. The two Kings Maiesties in forme as at the first, keepe on their way from Temple-Barre, all through the Strande, so to Charing-crosse, and thence to White-hall, where dismounting about seauen of the clocke in the Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, they feasted and reposed themselues there all that night.</p>
            <p>On Friday being the first day of August the Kings Maiestie of <hi>Denmarke</hi> being attended on by diuerse of our principall Nobilitie, past priuately to the Citie of London, vntill hee came to the greate Cathedrall Church of S. Paul, being onely to be admired for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17856:15"/> antiquitie, and hugenesse, rather for his beautie or curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ositie, and yet there be some things beyond sodaine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, as both his stately ascentions and the artificiall workemanship of diuers faire Windowes and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Tombs. Then his Maiestie went to the toppe of the steeple, from whence he might take the prospect and full view of the whole Citie, whose outstretched limmits I make no doubt, but inflamed him both with delight and admiration.</p>
            <p>After his Maiestie had beheld this famous Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he went to behold the Roiall Exchange, which being founded &amp; built at the charges of a subiect, may verie wel be ranckt and rekconed amongst the greatest Monuments preserued in any ferraine Nation: From thence his Maiestie went vntill he came to the Tower, where entring, he beheld the strengths, glories, riches, and other antient monuments preserued within that place, such as I do not think any christian king or other whatsoeuer is able to boast of any house cōparable to it in greatnes, strength, and most strange furnishmēts: one part of it containing the principall munition or store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house for al maner of warlike preparations, as ordināce of all sorts, euen frō the double Canon, to the hand Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll, &amp; all things whatsoeuer, which belongeth to any of their seueral vses: also horsmēs staues, pikes, halberts, browne bils, bowes, arrowes, armour innumerable, or what engines soeuer hath at any time been practised in our English wars: but to behold the infinite number of iron bullets of all sorts &amp; sises, made for the great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, lying in huge heaps, wold put an ignorant mind into much astonishment: there is in an other part, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17856:15"/> mint, &amp; places for the triall of mettals, a thing more thē strange to them that are not accustomed to such sights: in an other place are all the ancient records, charters, &amp; especial euidence of this kingdom: in another place, the wardrope, robes vsually worne by all the former kings and Queens of this nation, where if one obserue the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral fashions, embroderies, cuts, adornations, riches beauty, brauery, &amp; comely plainnes, which time hath brought forth, altred, &amp; renued, it wold not only moue admire, but euen inchant with the weight of seuerall considerations: there is another part of the Tower, the treasurie or iewel house, which how it is fraught or sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I haue herd diuers miraculously speak: but because I haue not with mine own eies beheld, I wil only ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin it is such, so excellent, &amp; not to be equalled, as wel may be seeme the dignitie and greatnes of so rich &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a kingdome: to cōclude, in this house which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like a little citie: within it selfe, are all the most me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable monuments which any former time hath left worthy to be remēbred: after the kings maiesty of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> had taken full view of this goodly castle or chief strength of our citie, &amp; what else was thought worthy of his royall presence in the citie, he departed backe to his own court, which then was held at Sōmerset house in the stand, &amp; frō thēce to white-hal where he lodged.</p>
            <p>On Saterday being the second day of August, both the Kings Maiesties road in the morning to Maribone Parke, where they hunted, where after they had killed diuerse Bucks, they returned to White-hall, and from thence in the afternoone departed to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where they feasted all Sunday being the third day of August.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17856:16"/>
            <p>On munday being the fourth day of August it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed our Kings Maiestie himselfe in persō, and the Kings Maiestie of <hi>Denmarke</hi> likewise in person, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his estate to runne at the ring in the Tilt-yard at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> approued to all Iudgements, that Maiestie is neuer vnaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with vertue: for there in the presence of all his behoulders, he tooke the ring fower seuerall times, and would I thinke haue done the like foure score times, had he runne so many courses.</p>
            <p>On Tuesday being the fift day of August, and the great festiuall for our Kinges Maiesties preseruation from <hi>Gowries</hi> treasons: The Kinges Maiestie of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> ran at the Tilt in person, and diuers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble personages; where his Maiestie exprest an able and induring bodie, how it was gouernd by an inuincible mind, inricht with all the artes and graces due to his high birth and office, there was that day also great Beare-baiting, Bull-baitinge and other sports: there was also great wrastling and exersises of force, betweene Deuonshire and Cornwall, against Suffolke and Norfolke, wherein Suffolke and Norfolke was reputed to haue the preheminence: thither came also all the maisters of of the noble science of Defence, but because the day was then spent, they were apointed to come the next morning by six of the clocke in the morning being wednesday the sixt of August, where what passed you must expect in your next aduertismēt, theise former tastes being of all the passages, as yet and hitherto effected.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17856:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>